A Guide to the Jesse Belle Rittenhouse Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8449
Jesse Belle Rittenhouse Collection 1902-1932
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8449
ca. 50 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit 1963 Dec 17 [ 1966 Nov 30 ]
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, " The Star ", 1919 Dec 28; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Tenants ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Transience ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Star ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Unrest ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Dream ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Protest ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Alter ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Two That Pass ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Fame and the Muse ", TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Seven Songs ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Magic ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Veil ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Transformation ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Miracle ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Unsung ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Wall ", n. d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to [ Curtis Hidden Page], Tuesday; TNS, 1 p.
    [Accompanies preceding poems, indicating they are "passing moods -that will not pass."]
- Letters
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1902 Oct 2; ALS, 4 p.
    [Expresses regret at missing his visit; invites him to join her at the home of Mr. and Mrs. C. D. Gilchrist in Arlington; describes her itinerary in coming weeks including lectures at Rutland and Bennington, Vermont and a Western lecture tour beginning in February.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1912 [Jul]; APCS, 1 p.
    [Describes travels in Italy to Rome, Florence, Venice and the lakes.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1914 Jan 5; ANS, 2 p.
    [Comments on his Christmas greeting, her trip to Europe and the many demands on her time since returning; invites him to her annual poets' party; expresses hope that Lizette Woodworth Reese and several others will be present and invites him to an Arts Club dinner.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1915 Jan 11; ANS, 2 p.
    [Announces the dates for her poets' party and the Poetry Society [of America] dinner; requests his presence at both; state her expectation that Alice Brown, Elsa Barker, Vachel Lindsey, Olive Dargan and the New York group will attend; expresses appreciation for the evening spent together; hopes she will have the opportunity to discuss with him a book Houghton wishes to publish.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1916 Jan 3; ANS, 2 p.
    [Invites him to her poets' party and [ Poetry Society of America] dinner; expects [Robert] Frost and [Edgar Lee] Masters to speak.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1920 Feb 18; ALS, 8 p.
    [Comments on letters received from him during his travels; outlines her lecture tour; describes the overwhelming hospitality she receives at every stop and the difficulty of writing poetry under such circumstances; expresses desire to lecture less and write more; describes the Poetry Society [of America] dinner attended by Lawrence Housman, Siegfried Sassoon, [William Butler] Yeats, Gilbert [Cannon], Yone Noguchi; comments on the ghostly presence of those no longer there: Edith Thomas, Joyce Kilmer, and [Madison] Cawein. ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1924 Feb 8; ALS, 9 p.
    [Thanks him for the inscribed book of Japanese poetry; expresses her admiration for it; mentions a young cousin, Arthur Armstrong, who will be attending Dartmouth, her living accommodations with her mother at Carmel, completing
    The Little Book of Modern British Verse
    and plans for beginning "Pioneering for Poetry"; states plans to marry Clinton Scollard and divide the year between California and the Berkshires. ]
  - Announcement of the marriage of Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Clinton Scollard, 1924 Mar 20; Note
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Jan 22; TLS, 2 p.
    [Regrets missing the events of the Poetry Society [of America] and [Anne Hempstead] Branch's reception due to her mother's poor health; describes her literary life in Winter Park, [Florida] where she is president of the Poetry Society of Florida and teaches at Rollins college; mentions other writers in the area: Percy [MacKaye], Robert Herrick, Mary Aldis, Cale Young Rice, Alice Hegan Rice, [Irving] Bacheller and his wife, Fred Lewis Pattee and [Hamilton] Holt. ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Mar 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Comments on Poetry Society [of America] election of trustees; describes her activities as President of the Poetry Society [of Florida], teaching at Rollins College; states her intention to attend spring meetings [of the Poetry Society of America]; mentions other writers living in the [ Winter Park] area: Percy MacKaye, Cale Young Rice, Alice Hegan Rice, Irving Bacheller, Robert Herrick as well as noted people in other fields; sends a program of the
    Animated Magazine
    . ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Mar 21; TLS, 1 p.
    [Requests that he act as a judge in the Ponce de Leon Prize contest in the Poetry Society of Florida, the other judges being Lady [Leona ?] Speyer and Margaret Widdenmer; describes the contest and method of judging; states her intention of attending the April meeting of the P[oetry] S[ociety of America] and her sense of anticipation at being in New York. ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Mar 25; TLS, 2 p.
    [Describes weather, social and intellectual life of [Winter Park], Florida; mentions the MacKayes, Rices, Robert Herrick, Robert Morse Lovett, the Bachellers, Albert Shaw, Oswald Garrison Villard, Lincoln Steffins, Raymond Robbins, Dr. [Hamilton] Holt, as well as the Institute of Statesmanship, which has brought Professor Bruce of Dartmouth; comments on [Martha Dickinson] Bianchi's talk on Emily Dickinson and the discovery of new Dickinson poems.] (Incomplete)
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Apr 3; TLS, 1 p.
    [Expresses pleasure that he will serve as judge [of a poetry contest]; explains the balloting procedure; states he is to receive poems from Arthur Guiterman; requests he select a third judge; mentions Leonora [Speyer ?], [Joseph] Auslander, or a member of the Poetry Society [of America] as possibilities; describes the poems a well done in general; writes that the best of them are by Rollins College students.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Jun 5; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses affairs of the [Poetry] Society [of America], the selection of chairman and secretary of the awards committee; indicates her vote will go to Witter and Grace Conkling; mentions the possibility of awarding 2 medals; mentions [Edwin Arlington] Robinson, [Robert] Frost and [Marian Nevins] MacDowell as possible recipients; suggests Robert Haven Schauffler or David Morton as potential candidates for president but urges Page to continue that office if possible.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, Jul 8; ALS, 4 p.
    [Comments on her surprise and delight at receiving a silver tea service from her friends; expresses her intention of writing personal thanks to the hundred contributors; states the poor health of her mother-in- law will prevent travel abroad this season; describes [Mrs. Scollard] as a brilliant woman, knowledgeable about politics, unlike herself who declares "the world is full of things more beautiful."]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, [ca. 1921] Aug 23; ALS, 11 p.
    [Describes injuries sustained from being thrown from a horse drawn trap and her subsequent convalescence; expresses hope that he will visit her home in Kent, Connecticut; describes alternate routes to her cottage; mentions her plans to travel to Grafton, Massachusetts, through the White Mountains to New York City; states a new collection of her poems,
    The Lifted Cap
    , will be published in autumn, including a group of poems written to Page.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, [ca. 1918] Nov 18; ALS, 4 p.
    [Scolds him for not sending her a picture of himself in uniform as he had to Elsa Parker; inquires about his life in the army; describes a recent illness, plans to travel and lecture in the West and South; mentions talks at Brooklyn Institute and her longing to go to Italy when travel resumes.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; AL, 8 p.
    [Describes her summer in the Green Mountains near Arlington, [Vermont] and her trip with another member of the Poetry Society [of America] Mr. Gilchrist and his wife, to bring Robert Frost to give a reading to a group of "summer folk"; states that on the way they stopped in Hanover, Connecticut; describes her trip to Page's home and her discovery that it had been sold; extolls the beauty of the area and her love of the mountains; describes her mother's recovery from serious illness, her own renewed vigor and upcoming lectures at Columbia [University], Indianapolis, the West and South.] (Incomplete)
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; ALS, 8 p
    [Discusses her mother's poor health, the upcoming poets' party; expects [William Butler] Yeats, [Siegfried] Sassoon, [Yone] Noguchi, Gilbert [Cannon ?], Lawrence Housman, the [John] Drinkwaters and Cecil Roberts to attend in addition to the "usual" American group; describes her participation in a luncheon at the Biltmore with John Drinkwater and Gilbert [Cannon ?]; comments on Cecil Roberts' endearing qualities; mentions that Professor [John Livingston] Lowes will speak at the annual dinner [of the Poetry Society of America?]; outlines her lecture tour of the West and South; indicates she is sending several poems ["
    Transformation
    , " "
    The Miracle
    Unsung
    , " and "
    The Wall
    "] inspired by Page's departure and describes the circumstances in which she wrote them.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; AL, 4 p.
    [Describes summer vacation with her aunt, Mrs. Taft, at Bear Island on Lake Winnipesakee, [New Hampshire] and at the MacDowell estate in Peterboro, [New Hampshire] with its lovely studios and living facilities.] (Incomplete)
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, [ca. 1932]; ANS, 2 p.
    [Printed card of thanks for Page's expression of sympathy; includes handwritten note describing Clinton [Scollard]'s apparent good health and the shock of his death; describes her activities in Winter Park, teaching at Rollins College, and editing Clinton's poems for MacMillan Co.; mentions Page's rare book venture.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; ANS, 2 p.
    [Indicates she is sending a "brief lyric" she finds charming; praises his poem "
    Lady from Tripoli
    " and encourages him to write more; comments on her reading of [August] Strindberg; mentions sending for "
    The Road to [Castaly ?]
    ".]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; ANS, 2 p.
    [Discusses "Harriet," whose dinner conflicted with another one given by the [ Poetry Society of America?]; mentions plans for the [John] Masefield luncheon and her hope Page will be present.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; ANS, 2 p.
    [Expresses pleasure that Page will be present at the "poets' evening" and dinner; comments on his retreat "among the pines" and her hopes of having the opportunity during his visit of hearing some of his work; lists those expected to attend the poets' night as Richard Burton, Clinton Scollard, Percy MacKaye, Josephine Peabody, Sara Teasdale, Harriet Monroe, Herman Hagedorn, Cale Young Rice, [Alice Hagen] Rice, [Martha Dickinson] Bianchi, Mark [Arms ?], Edith Thomas, [Frederick Ridgely] Torrence, [Charles Hanson] Towne, [Edwin Arlington] Robinson, and [William Bliss] Carman. ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; Postcard
    [Includes autograph; comments on her mother's illness, her lecture tour, an upcoming month of work at Brooklyn Institute, her hope Page will be coming to New York; praises his poem and urges him to write more; mentions a lecture in Montclair, [New Jersey] in postscript.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; TLS, 3 p.
    [Expresses gratitude for Page's help in judging poems competing for prize; mentions "
    Anaesthesia
    " the winner of the competition, "
    Exile
    The Flute of Krishna
    Protest
    Beauty Secret
    "; expresses her willingness to speak on the history of the Poetry Society [of America]; gives details on its founding; mentions Mrs. Markham, Miss Haste, Richard Burton, Madison Cawein, Mildred McNeil Sweeney, [Cale Young] Rice and [Alice Hagen] Rice and Maurice Browne. ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1924; Card, w/ANS
    [Sends Christmas greetings and the hope that work is going well; notes good notices on the [Ronsard ?].]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1926; Card, w/ANS
    [Sends Christmas greetings; comments on plans to spend the winter in Florida. ]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, 1927; Card, w/ANS
    [Compliments Page on his talk to the Poetry Society [of America] upon taking office; expresses confidence in his leadership; describes working with Rollins College students, to assist Dr. [Hamilton] Holt; states intention of sending Florida poets and poems to the P[oetry] S[ociety] of A[merica]; expresses hope that Page will like her
    Third Book of Modern Verse
    which she considers her best.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; Card, w/ANS
    [Invites him to her poets' party; comments on lectures given at Columbia and Brooklyn Institute; expresses anticipation of seeing Page and hearing of his work.]
  - Jessie Belle Rittenhouse to Curtis Hidden Page, n. d.; Card, w/ANS
    [Encourages him to come to Winter Park; mentions summer spent in Europe from which she "just escaped in time."]
- Miscellaneous
  - Poetry Society of America Committee on Awards and Fellowships, DS